倩女幽魂 第2集:人间道
十里平湖霜满天
Frost fills the sky over Ten Mile Lake
寸寸青丝愁华年
Silken threads anxious of youth
对月形单望相护
Looking at the moon and feeling lonely
只羡鸳鸯不羡仙
Envious of love, not of immortality
宁采臣
This pointing
你见到这幅画就好似见我一样
will remind you of me
聂小倩之墓？
Hsiao-tsing's grave?!
现在你相信小倩死了很久啦
Hsiao-tsing died long ago
小倩是鬼？
She's ghost?!
没错，我是鬼，但是我不想害人
Yes! I'm a ghost but I bring mortals no harm
当年，我客、死异乡
I died far away from my home
尸骨让千年树妖缠着不放
An evil spirit took by corpse and won't let me rest in peace
如果你肯救我的话
If you want to save me
就将我的尸骨搬走
move my bones away from here
那我就可以投胎转世
Then it will be possible for me to be reincarnated
小倩！
Hsiao-tsing!
我一定会救你！
I will save you
小倩！
Hsiao-tsing!
宁采臣！
Ning!
和我作对？我要你永不超生！
You dare oppose me?! I will never excuse you from death!
你放过他们！
Let them go, please
金刚经？呀…！
The Diamond Sutra!
走脱了，小倩，我们安全了！
We've escaped! Hsiao-tsing, we're safe!
天光了
Dawn is breaking
小倩，你快躲进骨灰盅里边去
Hsiao-tsing, hide in the tower of ashes
不要让阳光射到
If the sun's rays shine on you
不然的话，你不能投胎啦！
you'll never be reincarnated
宁采臣，永别！
Ning, good-bye forever!
希望小倩可以投胎做人
I hope that Hsiao-tsing will be reincarnated
我要回兰若寺，避开尘世
I must return to the Orchid Temple
有事就去兰若寺找我，珍重！
If you need me, you can find me there Take care!
那个年轻人是谁？
Who is that young man!
他就是后面街的那个穷书生
He's the poor scholar who lived two blocks away
他现在才回来，这个世界都变啦
Things have changed since he was last here
他不就是集宝斋派来收帐的那个小子
Wasn't he that shop's bill collector?
集宝斋已关门很久啦，他还懵然不知
He doesn't even know it went out of business long ago!
招待不周，招待不周
Welcome! Welcome!
收帐来了
The bill collector's here
收了多少啦？
How much money did you collect?
我们是捉逃犯的
We're here to catch escaped convicts
衙差！走…！
It's the police! Run!
追！
Pursue them!
你是不是周亚炳？
You're Bing Chow?!
这个好明显
You made a mistake
他有须我没有，我是好人呀！
He has a beard and I don't!
没须？剃了不就没有了
You shaved it off!
捉他回去领奖金
Take him back and collect the reward
进去！
Get in!
你们冤枉我，我没有犯法
I haven't committed any crime!
放我出去，冤枉呀！
Let me go I've been wrongly accused!
放我出去，我不是周亚炳，冤枉呀！
You made a mistake I'm not Bing Chow!
冤枉呀！
I am wrongly accused!
我叫宁采臣，不是周亚炳
My name is Ning, not Bing Chow
老伯，请问你…
Old man may I ask who...
我和你一样，是人，命中注定要坐监
A man, just like you, fated to being imprisoned
这么悲观！
So pessimistic!
这都怪祖先无眼，叫我追求学问
It's all me elders' fault, insisting I get an education
等我长大了，写书做博学士
When I grew up, I was learned and wrote backs
谁知道写游记
But when I write of my travels
被人说我泄漏国家机密
I'm accused of revealing state secrets
写历史，说我借古讽今
When I write of history, they say I'm satirizing the present
好，那去注解兵法，又说我煽动作反
If I analyze military strategy, they say I'm planning a rebellion
唉！写神话好了吧
I can't even write fairy tales
却又说我导人迷信
for they accuse me of promoting superstition
最后唯有替人写传记
Finally, I wrote the biography of a powerful man
结果那个人被抓了，说是乱党
Then he was arrested, accused of being a rebel
我跟他一起被判终身监禁
We were both sentenced to life imprisonment
你说是不是命里注定要坐牢呢？
Wouldn't you say that prison is my fate?
蟑螂呀！
A cockroach!
哪里，哪里…
Where?
蟑螂？
Cockroach?!
你真浪费呀，蟑螂在这里是极品呀
You're really wasteful! The cockroaches here are of the best quality
这里没有山珍海味
There are no delicacies here
你多住一阵子
After you're been here a while
就会看到苍蝇都流口水了
you'll even salivate ever a housefly
老伯，你在这里困了多久？
Old man, how long have your been here?
刚来的时候，就像你一样
I was your age when I first arrived
现在变成我这样，你看多有性格！
Look how I've changed! Full of character!
那就是说坐了很久了
You've been here a long time!
救命呀！救命呀！冤枉呀！
Help! I am innocent!
我不是周亚炳，冤枉呀！
I'm not Bing Chow! I am innocent!
冤枉呀，我不是周亚炳呀！
You've made a mistake I'm not Bing Chow!
又发恶梦了，今次又梦见什么啦？
Another nightmare What did you dream this time?
我梦见你筋疲力尽的
I dreamt you were haggard and exhausted
筋疲力尽？
Exhausted?!
对呀，你就快会筋疲力尽了
True, you will soon be totally exhausted
晚晚发恶梦，你看看墙上的日历
You have nightmares every night Look at the calendar
你进来了这么久还不适应
You've been here so long and still can't adjust
再过一阵子你连自己姓周都记不起了
Soon you'll even forget that your last name is Chow
老伯，我不是姓周的
Old man, my last name isn't Chow!
周亚炳！
Bing Chow!
吃饭喇！
Supper!
好呀，好呀！
OK
鸡腿！鸡腿！
A chicken leg?!
啊，运气来了！
Happy days are here again!
老伯，只有一碗，你先吃吧！
Old man! There's only one bowl You eat first
你自己吃吧，我宁愿吃蟑螂
No, it's for you I'd rather eat cockroaches
吃完了再告诉你吧！
I'll tell you something when you've finished
我好久没吃鸡了
I haven't had chicken in a long time
怎么你涂了我的名字呢？老伯！
Old man, why are you carving my name?
告诉你，墙上有名之人
All these men
每一个都吃过鸡腿
ate chicken legs
这只鸡叫做夺命鸡
We call that chicken a headless chicken
吃过了就要被抓上刑场去砍头的
After you've eaten it, they chop off your head!
砍头？
Chop off your head?!
周亚炳，周亚炳，钱财送上黄泉路
Bing Chow, we have no personal quarrel
有仇不要找我报
Don't come back from the grave and seek revenge on me!
老伯，人家说午时斩首
They behead people at noon
怎么会三更半夜行刑的呢？
It's now the middle of the night
一定那些高官子弟犯了罪
Some official's son got in trouble
找人做替死鬼
and they're looking for a substitute
三更半夜的
At night
随便斩那一个都没人知道
the executioner can't tell one from another
世间上真的没有公理
Is there no justice in the world?
原来做好人是没有好报的
Is there no reward for being a good man?
不关我的事…
It is of no concern to me
我做人向来两袖清风
I was always an honest man
能送的我都送给你
I'll give you whatever I can
这幅画是我一个亲人留给我
This painting was a gift from my dearest one
我去那儿都带着它
I don't want to part with it even in death
我没见过像你这么重感情的人
Young man, you have a good heart
物轻情义重，我还个礼给你
Let me give you a present
老伯，你这么好的学问
You are so learned
幸亏只是找我做替死鬼
It is fortunate that I die rather than you
你人这么好，死了太可惜了
You're a good man Such a pity you have to die
我死不可惜，你死了才可惜
It would be a pity if you died, not me
谁说的，那一个死都可惜
Anybody's death is a pity
你这种人世上已经少有了
You're a rare specimen
要是死了，那不就绝种了，不…
If you die, your type will be extinct
我有好久没放生了
It's been a long time since I set somebody free
这里有个地下通道，直通外面
This tunnel leads to the outside
你到了外面，可以重头来过
Go out and start anew
何必给假希望我呢
Don't give me such false hopes
如果可以直通外面，你早就出去了
If this is an escape route, why didn't you escape long ago?
我在这里写书，没有人来烦我
It's less troublesome for me to write my book here
写完了又可以随时拿出去给人家印
When I finish, then I'll escape and get it printed
你不用担心我的安危
Don't worry about me
这个包袱你带在身边
Always keep this bundle with you
年轻人，你出去了就不要再回来了
Once you're out of here never come back!
走呀…走呀！
Get going!
我走了你怎办？
What will happen to you after I've gone?
他们喜欢听我讲故事
They like hearing my stories
我的故事讲来讲去都讲不完
So long as I don't get to the story's end
所以不会斩我的
They'll never harm me
两个人少了一个，怎么过得了这关呢
But they'll accuse you of helping me escape
我就说前两天
I'll say you were put to death
被你们狱卒抓去做替死鬼了
for somebody else two days ago
他们就不敢查了，放心走吧！
They won't dare make a fuse
走呀！保重呀！
Go! Take care!
周亚炳，时辰到了，准备上路吧
Bing Chow! The time has come!
快点！…
Hurry up!
周亚炳！
Bing Chow!
死了！
He's dead
重见天日了，真是险过剃头！
I've escaped!
连坐骑都已准备好了
There's even a horse here waiting for me!
老伯真是神通广大
That old man
不知道是那位高人呢？
is really remarkable!
改天要好好的报答他才行
I must reply his kindness someday
喂，我的千里追呀…
Hey! That's my horse!
喂，真是笨，那一个骑上去都跑
What a stupid horse! Letting a stranger ride him!
害得我连洗手的时间都没有
I don't even have time to wash my hands!
你有你在上面跑，我有我在下面追
You think you're fast over land I'll go underground!
遁地！
Open sesame!
这么大雨到那儿去避呢？
I must find a place to get out of this downpour!
有人家了，先避一下
Good! A House!
开门呀，开门呀！
Open the door!
正气山庄
"Righteous Villa"
有没有人呀？
Anybody home?
一、二、三、四、五、六、七、八
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
八副棺材，那不是一家人全在这里
Eight Coffins! Must be the whole family
我不会打扰你们的，我只是借宿一宵
I won't disturb you I just want to stay the night
你们用不着起来招呼我
Don't bother to get up I'll take care of myself
我说过不用招呼我了，请回吧！…
I told you not to go to any trouble. Please go back!
回你的头呀
The way you rush about
你在上面转来转去，四处跑
in no fixed direction!
搞到我在下面团团转
I had a hard time following you underground
你到那儿去没目标吗？
Don't you have any idea where you're going?
你面色这么难看，一定是死得很惨
Your face looks so horrible, you must have suffered a painful death
如果你像我那样在下面追了一整天
If you'd rushed around underground all day like me
你就是不死都上不来了
you wouldn't have the energy to come back to the surface
我不认识你，你干吗跟着我？
I don't know you Why are you following me?
我也不认识你，你为什么骑我的马？
I don't know you either so why did you take my horse?
原来这只马是你的
That's your horse?
我还以为这只马是老伯的
I thought it was the old man's
老伯，老伯你也该问一声
Still you should have asked
见马就骑
before taking it
那你是人罗，对不起，是个误会
You're alive! Sorry! It's all a misunderstanding
有什么要我帮忙的，你说好了
If there's anything I can do to help, just let me know
还声东击西的暗算我，幸亏我反应快
Enough of your tricks! A good thing my reactions are so fast
朋友，朋友，你也不过想借宿一宵
Friend, you need a place to stay the night
这里有瓦遮头，就这里好了
Here there's a roof over your head Might as well stay here
要是我睡着了
How do I know
我怎么知道你做些什么？
what you'd do after I fell asleep?
我早料到是外面漏水
I knew it!
大家分清界线，我在隔壁
Let's draw up some boundaries I'm staying next door
有什么话大声讲，不要过来找我
If you have something to say, shout it! Don't come over
我有好几个月没洗澡了
I haven't bathed in a long time
什么人？
Who is it?
是不是人呀？
Are you a mortal?
隔壁的朋友，快点起来呀
Hey, friend next door!
这里有鬼呀
Get up! There's ghosts!
快点起来，听见了没有？
Get up! Do you hear me?
快点起来呀！
Hurry and get up!
一声不响的，一定是走了
Not a sound Maybe he left already
真的这么凶，无孔不入
What a nuisance!
朋友，很猛的鬼呀，快点走呀！
Friend, there are fierce ghosts here!
鬼？天地法灵，逐鬼驱魔令
Ghosts? I'll use my magic to banish them!
站过一旁去，天地法灵，逐鬼驱魔令
Ghosts and goblins I order you to leave!
老兄，原来你懂法术的
Oh, you understand the occult!
我鼻子是专闻妖魔鬼怪的
My nose is sensitive to other worldly spirits...
怎么一点味道都没有？
So why do I smell nothing now?
避开！
Get out of the way!
金锣脱锁！
Abracadabra!
你们算什么鬼呀，一点鬼味都没有
Strange! Not even a hint of ghostly odor!
叭呢叭呢吽，风火雷电霝
Abracadabra! Hocus-pocus flash!
正飞过来，走！
They're coming Leave!
搞了半天，原来是假的
You're not even real ghosts!
浪费了我的法术
Wasting my occult talents!
假的？
Phonies?
走后门！
Want to trick me?
幸好有你的腰带
A good thing you have a waistband
不要过来呀，我不客、气了
Stay away from me!
掉了…
I'm falling...
不要接着我，不要接着我
Stop hugging me!
放手呀！
Let go!
放手我就要掉下去了
If I let go, I'll fall!
再不放手，我…
If you don't let go, I'll...
小倩？
Hsiao-tsing?!
小倩！
神兵火急，急急如律令，替我定！
Hocus-pocus heebie-jeebie! I order you to freeze!
定！
Freeze!
我定！
小倩，是你呀？
Hsiao-tsing, is that you?
你这是什么妖术，放了他们
What kind of black magic is that? Let them go!
要不然我杀了他
Otherwise I'll kill him
啊…我定！
Oh... Freeze!
好，请动手，我根本不认识他
Kill him! He's no friend of mine!
诸葛卧龙！
Elder Chu Kot!
先生，你就是诸葛卧龙老前辈？
Chu Kot?! Are you Elder Chu Kot traveling incognito?
诸葛什么？
Elder who?
晚辈失礼了
Your disciple is deeply sorry
晚辈？
Disciple?!
诸葛卧龙？
Elder Chu Kot?!
小倩，是我呀，你不认得我了？
Hsiao-tsing, it's me! Don't you recognize me?
我们是忠良之后，本人是傅青风
We come from a good family My name is Windy
她是舍妹傅月池
This is my younger sister, Moon
诸葛前辈！
Elder Chu Kot
前辈，见到你我们就有救了
Elder, you can save us
我爹是前任礼部尚书傅天仇
My father is Lord Fu the ex-Minister of Rites
被朝廷奸人所害，要押解上京处斩
He was framed. They're now transporting him to be executed
我们想在半路上救回我爹
We want to attack the transport wagon and rescue him
你是博学多才的诸葛卧龙
You are the learned and brilliant Chu Kot
而你们两位是朝廷的忠臣义士
You two are loyal imperial warriors
大家都是名人
Everyone is an eminent personage
现在轮到我介绍我自己了
Now it's my turn to introduce myself
我就是…解！
I am... Spell!
失礼，失礼
My name is Autumn
在下是昆仑派后学术士，知秋一叶
from the Kunlun sect
前辈的大作我全都拜读过
I've read everything that the Elder has written
我学法术只是对付那些妖魔
I only use my magic to battle demons
国家大事我是不理的
I never get involved in affairs of state
拜见诸葛前辈
We pay our respects to Elder Chu Kot
我是宁采臣，不是诸葛卧龙呀
My name is Ning, not Chu Kot
传闻前辈神龙见首不见尾
I can tell you are clever
不会随便暴露自己的身份
Clever people do not always reveal their identities
我们在心里记得前辈是那位就行了
Anyway, in our hearts we know who you really are
我要怎么讲你才相信呢？
How can I make you believe me?
不需要多说，大家记着
No need for you to say anything Everybody remember...
由现在开始
From now on
宁采臣就是诸葛卧龙
Elder Chu Kot will be known as Ning
诸葛卧龙就是宁采臣
Chu Kot is Ning
不错！
Yes!
大家向天发誓
We will now take an oath
谁要是把这个重要的秘密泄露出去
Whoever reveal their identities
我们就将他碎尸万段
will be chopped up into 10,000 pieces
是！
Yes!
这马被你骑过，我都觉得很荣幸
Such an honour that you rode my horse!
小倩，你还记得那幅画和诗吗？
Hsiao-tsing, do you remember this painting and poem?
小倩？诗？
Hsiao-tsing? Poem?
念诗了…快拿笔来
He's reciting poetry Quickly, pen and paper
一人记一句，前辈有暗示啦
We must record what he says Elder is giving us a hint
我有笔，快点！快点！
Hurry!
十里平湖霜满天
Frost fills the sky over Ten Mile Lake;
寸寸青丝愁华年
Silken threads anxious of youth
对月形单望相护
Looking at the moon and feeling lonely
只羡鸳鸯不羡仙
Envious of lovers, not of immortality
真是深不可测
Very profound!
什么十里呀？什么十里呀？
What does "ten mile" mean?
十里？是什么意思？
Ten mile!
高，果然真的高
It is all very deep
前辈的意思太深奥啦
His words are too profound
十里，十里，那就是十里亭了
Ten Mile? That must mean Ten Mile Pavilion
怎样？
What do you mean?
这里附近有个十里亭？
There's a Ten Mile Pavilion near hear
对呀，姐姐…，十里就是十里亭
That's right! Sister, "ten mile' refers to Ten Mile Pavilion
在附近！
It's nearby
我明白了，这里不远有个十里亭
I understand Ten Mile Pavilion is not far from here
霜满天那就是霜降
"Frost" refers to Frost's Descent
一年有二十四个节气
Each year has 24 climatic periods...
秋暑露秋寒霜降
After the autumnal equinox comes the frost...
今天适逢霜降之日
and today is the day of Frost's Descent
前辈的意思
Elder is telling us that
是暗示我爹会被押经十里亭
father will be transported past Ten Mile Pavilion
叫我们到那里去救他
He's telling us to rescue him there
前辈真是神机妙算，我爹有救了
Elder is truly perceptive We can save father
让我们猜中了
We had it right!
好呀！
Good
好痛呀！
It hurts!
怎么样？快起来呀！…
What's the matter? Get up!
探子报！
Reporting!
青风姑娘
Miss Windy!
傅大人将会在今晚被押经十里亭
Your father will pass the Ten Mile Pavilion tonight
我们早就知道了
We already know that
前辈真的有先见之明
Elder is truly brilliant!
不过，前辈
But what about the rest of the poem?
还剩下的两句诗又暗示什么呢
What do those two stanzas mean?
是三句呀！
Three stanzas
现在暗示什么都没用了
The meaning doesn't matter now
你们要怎么想就怎么想好了
Interpret it in any way you desire
明白，就是说做人要有主见
He means that we should have our own views...
不要只听人家的，是不是这个意思？
not just listen to what other people say, right?
那听前辈的算不算听人家呢？
So, should we still listen to what Elder says?
这怎么相同呢？
Not only listen
前辈的说话要记住，不断、揣摩
but take notes and ponder his meaning
将来开枝散叶，代代相传
We must pass his wisdom on to future generations
是！
Right!
前辈，告辞了！
Time to leave!
我送你们出去
Good-bye
我们出发往十里亭！
We're off to Ten Mile Pavilion
是，出发往十里亭！
Yes. We're off to Ten Mile Pavilion
青风姑娘，小倩的画还给我
Miss Windy, please return Hsiao-tsing's painting to me
是，前辈
Yes, Elder
你叫我小倩，是不是暗示我用假名字
When you call me Hsiao-tsing, is that a hint that I need a pseudonym?
那你以后叫我小倩好了
From now on, my name is Hsiao-tsing
就算小倩投胎转世
If Hsiao-tsing were reincarnated
现在只不过是个婴孩
she would now be a babe in arms
她不是小倩！
She's not Hsiao-tsing!
你在偷看什么？
What are you spying on?
我…我…没什么
Me? Nothing
姐姐，你也在偷看什么？
What are you spying on?
我在看你刚才偷看的，看完了，出发
I wanted to see what you were spying on Time to go!
姐姐，你猜你下个月嫁的那个马公子
Do you think your fiance, Prince Ma...
有没有他那么潇洒？
is as handsome as Elder?
我们是指腹为婚
We were betrothed before birth
我怎知道他长得怎么样呢？
How do I know what he looks like?
人家说有缘是不是这个意思？
Is that what people mean by fate?
你在说谁跟谁？
Who are you referring to?
没有，我只是觉得我好幸福
Oh, nobody It's just that I fell so fortunate
幸福？我看你连口水都流出来了
Fortunate? You're frothing at the mouth!
妖气！
Evil spirits!
是手印还是脚印，好夸张呀
Is this a foot print or a hand print?
找到那只妖怪不就知道了
We'll know when we find the monster
不错！
Right!
还害了人呢
It even harmed a man
放在这里太可惜了，拿去给前辈看看
What a pity to leave it here Better show it to Elder
好了…这里真的有鬼
OK!
真的有鬼呀，前辈！
There really are ghosts in this place!
是什么东西？
What is that?
是死尸，是那只鬼把他害成这样
A corpse! It's all that ghost's fault
你还抱着他，快放下吧！
Don't hug it. Put it down
这个人怎么会死得这么惨？
How did this person die so pitifully?
就是说这只鬼好凶
I'd say this an evil ghost
那股气味好难闻罗
The odor is very strong
来了！
It's back!
是不是来找我们的？
Is it looking for us?
快用你的法术呀
Use your "freeze" magic
好！
Right!
定心咒，神兵火急
I command you to freeze!
急急如律令，这就行了！
Heebie-jeebie! Freeze! That'll stop him!
这怎么用呢？
How do you do it?
你看到那只鬼的时候
When you see a ghost
就这样叫一声定
shout "freeze"
就这样叫一声定，这就行了吗？喂
Like this? Freeze! Is that right? Hey!
喂…，不好了，你的咒是怎样解的？
Oh, no! How do you lift the spell?
要想个方法沟通一下才行
I have to think of a way to communicate with him
没办法，让我试一试
What can I do? Let's try this...
如果我做得对
If I'm right
你的眼珠就上下转动
move your eyes up and down
这就对了，好极了！
That's right! Fantastic!
如果做得不对，眼珠就左右转
If I'm wrong, move them from left to right
对，对！
Great!
解咒的方法是一种手势
Will a hand gesture lift the spell?
不是上下，又不是左右，歪的？…
What? Not up and down or left to right
你不要玩了，好不好？
Don't joke with me
等那只鬼来到就来不及了
If we wait too long, that monster will get us
解咒在哪里？
Does lifting the spell
是不是在胸口，让我看看
have to do with an acupuncture point?
你的眼转得这么快，比走马灯还快呀
Your eyes are moving faster than a revolving lantern!
我明白了
I understand!
你想用激将法激我打动你是吗？
You're provoking me into hitting you
好…那你就得捱一下了
OK. I'm going to hit you now
我不迁就你的
Ready or not, here it comes!
走呀！
Let's get out of here!
Come on!
你好重呀
You're too heavy
我抱不动了
I can't carry you
拖吧
Drag it!
拖也不够快
Dragging you isn't fast enough either
好，我就把你藏到阁楼去
Better hide upstairs
叫你不要玩了，玩成这样子
I told you not to fool around at a time like this
那只鬼好高，一站高就看到我们了
That monster is so tall, it'll see us if he stands up straight
老兄呀，你这个咒究竟怎么解呢
How can I undo the spell?
怎么解？
How do I lift the spell?
里边安全点，快躲进去
It's safer inside Better hide yourself quick
我叫你躲进去嘛
I told you to hide inside
为什么你走下去呢，下面这么危险
Why did you go down there, where it's so dangerous?
定心咒，定！
Try the "freeze" curse! Freeze!
来…我们继续撞吧！
Let's continue with out guessing game
你越来越重，我快要扶不了你了
You're getting heavier and heavier Can't carry you much longer
趁这只怪兽定住了
Since that monster isn't here...
我们再来试试怎么解好不好？
Let's try to lift the spell
是不是跟这个咒有关？
Does it have anything to do with this amulet?
是？跟着怎么样？
Yes?! What then?
跟着就指着我，指着我就可以解咒了
Point at me. Point at me and the curse will be lifted
指呀！
Point!
怎么解呢？…怎么解呀？
How do I undo the spell?
问你也是白问，自己想好了
No good asking you! I must figure it out for myself
哗！…定！
Freeze!
不许动！…动呀，动呀！
Don't move! Move! Move!
不许动！…
Don't move!
我真不明白
Why does he
为什么他一会儿就没事了
"unfreeze" so quickly
而你就这么久都一点不动呢？
but you haven't moved for so long?
难道…我指着这符，就在想
Do you mean... I pointed to this amulet...
然后就问你怎么解…
Then I asked you how to lift the spell...
他就动了，定！
And he moved! Freeze!
我顶着，快走呀！
I'll take care of it Get out of here fast!
终于也解了
Finally lifted the spell!
走呀！
Get out of here!
风雷地动令，开路！
Abracadabra! Open up a way out!
先走开，我来对付它
Out of the way! I'll take care of it!
叭呢叭呢吽！
Abracadabra!
风火雷电鬼！
Hocus pocus!
叭呢叭呢吽！
Abracadabra!
风火雷电鬼！
Hocus pocus!
天地法灵，逐鬼驱魔令
I order all ghosts to be expelled!
好厉害，不怕我的符咒
Wow! It doesn't fear my incantations!
看招！
Take this!
还动！
It's still moving!
逐鬼驱魔令！风雷地动令！
I order all ghosts to be expelled! Hocus pocus!
这样还让它的上半身走脱了
Even when it's chopped up he can still run away!
它可能随时会回来的
It could still come back at any time
前辈，你快点离开这里，我去追他
Elder, get out of here I'll pursue it!
你小心点啊！
Be careful!
遁地！
Earth, open up!
天亮了！
Dawn is breaking
急急如律令！定！
Heebie-jeebie! Freeze!
定！
Freeze!
遁地！
Earth, open up!
想走！
Want to leave!
好厉害！
Wow!
法术都来不及用
My magical powers are no good at all
遁地！
Earth, open up!
是个术士？
A magician?!
看镖！
Take this!
喂，停呀，停呀！
Hey! Stop! Stop!
你傻的，叫你停都不停
Are you stupid? I told you to stop!
你我素不相识，为什么要拼命呢？
We don't even know each other Why are we fighting?
我们的法术是用来对付妖魔鬼怪的
I learned magic to deal with evil spirits
你再不停手，我就用法术定了你
If you don't stop, I'll use my magic to "freeze" you
你是哪路人马，挡我的去路？
Why are you blocking my way?
我在下面捉鬼
I was just taking a rest after battling some ghosts
上来透透气这还说我挡路？
and you say I'm blocking your way
天黑了那只妖怪走出来，你们就麻烦
When that monster makes a run for it tonight, you'll be in deep trouble
兄弟！
Brother!
叫我法师
Call me Master
法师身手不凡
Master, your skill is extraordinary
如果肯为朝廷效力
If you worked for the imperial court
前途一定无可限量
your future would be boundless
叫我法师，就知道我是出家人
You know that I'm a Taoist monk
你们凡人喜欢升官发财
Seeking wealth and position is
我要四大皆空
for the likes of you mere mortals
我不跟你们一般见识，遁地！
I don't want to end up like you... Earth, open up!
真是年少有为
Well done, young man!
报告千户
Hu, our hourses' hoofs-are rigid
我们的马匹都四蹄直伸，打也不动
They won't move!
一定是那个术士作的法术
It must be that monk's magic at work!
他说天黑之后有妖怪，大家小心
He said there are evil spirits Be careful!
是！
Yes!
傅大人！
Lord Fu!
朝廷里的恩怨
There's nothing I can do about
不是我一介武夫所能干预
squabbles in the imperial court
通常是非都是真相不白
It's hard to tell right from wrong
我只是奉命行事
I'm just following orders
不过你可以放心
But don't worry
我一定保你一路平安
I'll make sure your journey is safe
回到京城之后
After we get to the capital
皇上怎么处置你，就不是我的责任了
whatever the emperor does to you is not me responsibility
上路！
Let's go!
请问，哪里有东西吃呢？
Where can I get something to eat?
老板，来一碗最便宜的
Please give me a bowl of your cheapest food
什么？最便宜？
What? The cheapest?
坐吧，坐吧！
Sit down!
饿死了就不用花钱啦，穷鬼！
If you're starving don't waste your money
给个脸我看看…
Show me your face
走，走！
Go!
站着！站着！
Stand up
头抬高点，抬高点！
Don't lower your head
走！
Go!
别走呀！…
Don't run away!
别走！
Don't move!
和尚？
Monks?
别走呀！
Don't move!
站着！
Stand still!
走开！
Out of the way!
滚开呀！…
Get out of the way!
这是什么法术呀？
What kind of magic is this?
是青风他们…等等呀！
It's Windy... Wait!
回来呀！
Come back!
喂！
Hey!
官兵昨晚避过十里亭
The soldiers never come to Ten Mile Pavilion last night
快点回正气山庄埋伏
Rush back to Righteous Villa and lie in ambush for them
喂！喂！
Hey!
回正气山庄？正气山庄有鬼呀
Back to Righteous Villa? It's haunted!
回来呀！
Come back!
前辈！前辈！
Elder! Elder!
不知道前辈走了没有
I wonder if Elder has already gone?
大家到处找一找
Better search for him
是！
Yes!
你猜官兵押着爹会不会已经过了这里
Do you think father's transport has already passed by here?
不会，照估计他们要天黑之后才会到
No. They're not supposed to reach here until after dark
青风姑娘，里面好多地方都被毁烂了
Miss Windy, the villa has been ransacked
一定是前辈消灭了我们留下的痕迹
I'm sure Elder did it to remove any traces of our presence
大家装置机关，准备应战
Set everything up Prepare to attack
是！
Yes!
大家快点动手，去那边！
Hurry up! Over there!
来者何人？
Who is it?
我是宁采臣，宁采臣？
I'm Ning Ning?
原来是前辈
Oh, it's Elder!
正气庄有鬼呀！
This villa is haunted
有鬼？
Haunted?
青风姑娘呢？
Where is Miss Windy?
在里面！
Inside
有鬼？
Ghosts?
真的鬼？
Real ghosts?
青风姑娘！
Miss Windy!
衣服呢？
My clothes!
青风姑娘！
Miss Windy!
前辈，他们说你来了！
Elder, they said you came
月池姑娘！
Miss Moon!
你是谁？
Who are you?
前辈，我认得你的背影了
Oh, it's Elder I recognize your back
前辈…
Elder...
我…
I...
原来你剃了胡子是这么…
With your beard shaved off you're so, so...
是呀…
Yes
我姐姐看到你这样子
When my sister sees you
一定会替我高兴了
she'll be so happy for me
高兴？
Happy?!
对了，你进来的时候有没有见我姐姐
When you came in, did you see my sister?
你姐姐？…没有，没有…
Your sister? No, No!
姐姐！…姐姐！…姐姐！
Sister! Sister! Sister!
你笑什么？
What are you grinning about?
非礼勿视！
It is improper to look
月池姑娘
Ms Moon
有些东西你是不能看的
There are some things you shouldn't look at
你没事吧！
You're all right!
前辈剃了胡子，我真的认不出来了
I didn't recognize Elder with his beard shaved off
是吗？那我也要去看看
Really? I must see for myself
前辈，你有话就直说好了
Elder, if you have something to say, just say it
你这样暗示，我好怕呀！
It scares me when you hint at things
我好冷呀！
I'm cold
你的脸这么热，还说冷？
Your face is so hot how can you be cold?
前辈，我们这样会不会太快了？
Wouldn't this be faster?
还不够快，再快点更好
Not fast enough Faster would be better
还要再快点？那…好吧！
Faster?! OK
前辈！
Elder...
前…辈说他好冷呀
Elder said he was cold
冷？
Cold?
前辈，你太辛苦了
Elder, you're overly exerting yourself
请问两位，有没有见过青风姑娘呢？
Have you seen Miss Windy?
没有，我也在找她
No, I'm looking for her, too
她到哪里去了呢？
Where did she go?
上面有声音，上去看看
There's noise coming from upstairs Let's go up for a look
不要上去呀
Don't go up there
奇怪！怎么没人？
Strange! Nobody up here
可能在隔壁，过去看看
Maybe it's next door Let's go over and look
你们乱哄哄的做什么？
What are you doing?
宁采臣前辈回来找我…们呀
Sister, Elder came back to find me... us
你看你们，衣衫不整的，成何体统呀
Why are your clothes so disheveled?
以后不许你们这样失礼
Don't be so impolite in the future
青风姑娘，这个山庄有鬼呀
Miss Windy, this villa is haunted
我们以后还用得着扮鬼吗？
Do we still have to pretend to be ghosts?
无论如何，我们一定要在这里等爹
No matter what, we must wait here for father
是绝对不能离开的
We mustn't leave
在这危急的时刻
In this moment of danger
我们要挺起胸膛，不用畏惧
we must thrust out our chests and be fearless
大家要肝胆相照，你们说对不对？
We must be utterly devoted to our cause
挺起胸膛，不用畏惧
Elder, let's go in
前辈！挺起胸膛？
Elder! Thrust out our chests
你的衣服后面破了
Your clothes are torn in the back
定心咒怎么写呢？
How do you write the "freeze" incantation?
我不是偷看他
I didn't spy on him
其实我根本不知道他在外面
I didn't even know he was outside
小心呀，用绳子绑住你的心吧
Better tie your heart down
再不绑住，快要飞出去了
Otherwise, it might fly away!
绑得住我一定绑
If I could lie it down, I would!
这样差不多了…定！
This is how you do it... Freeze!
成功啦！
It works!
这个就叫“定心咒 ”
This is the "freeze" incantation
如果你看到妖怪
If you see that monster
你就向着它叫“定 ”，就行了
do this and he'll freeze in his tracks
是不是这样？
Like this?
千万不要乱定，解咒就辛苦了
Don't do it haphazardly This spell is hard to reverse
把手拿来！是！
Give me your hand. Yes!
姐姐，什么声音？
Sister, what's that sound?
在上面呀！青风！
It's coming form up there. Windy!
青风，来，手给我
Windy, give me your hand
前辈，你是不是应该叫我小倩？
Elder, shouldn't you be calling me Hsiao-tsing?
小倩也好，青风也好，你用不着害羞
Whether I call you Hsiao-tsing or Windy there's no need to be bashful
刚才的事，我会替你保守秘密的
I'll never reveal what happened just now
我真替你紧张呀
I was really anxious on your behalf
老实说
Actually, I kissed you because
我亲你一下，是因为控制不了
I couldn't control myself
幸亏你走得快
Fortunately you made a quick get-away
否则被月池看见你没穿衣服
Otherwise, if Moon had seen you undressed and with me...
就算是诸葛卧龙都解释不了啦
it would be hard to explain even if I were Elder Chu Kot
来，手给我！
Give me your hand
月池！
Moon?!
月池，怎么你也在吗？
Moon, what are you doing here?
我刚想找你
I was looking for you
你们不用解释了
Don't bother explaining
月池！
Moon!
小倩，不是，青风，把手给我
No! Windy! Give me your hand
小倩与你无缘，我早就许配了马家
We're not fated for each other I'm betrothed to Lord Ma's son
你许配了人家了吗？
You're betrothed?
我们不会有结果的
We weren't meant for each other
你要找的应该是月池，不是我
You should be looking for Moon, not me
青风，一个个来嘛，我两个都要找
Windy, one at a time I'm after both of you
月池姑娘，天黑了，把手给我
Miss Moon, it's getting dark Give me your hand
你去找姐姐吧！
Go to my sister instead
我先找你再去找她，你快把手给我
I'll go to her next Quick, give me your hand
前辈，你太花心了
Elder, aren't you the playboy!
我们两个你只可以拣一个
You can only choose one of us
我是不会跟姐姐争的
I'm not going to compete with my sister
争什么，用不着争呀
No need to compete
我写完你就会去写她
When I finish with you I'll go to her
前辈，我有些心事要跟你讲
Elder, there is something I must tell you
其实感情是一件好奇怪的事
Actually, love is a strange thing
我一看到你
My heart beats wildly
我的心就砰、砰、砰的跳
when I look at you
我现在连望你一眼的勇气都没有
I don't even have the courage to glance at you
我怕一望见你，我的心就跳了出来
I'm afraid that my heart would jump right out
跟你在一起，你叫我去死我都愿意
I'd be willing to die if that's what you wanted
永远不分开就好了
As long as I can be with you forever and ever part
救命呀！…
Help!
什么事？
What's that?
天黑了，那只妖怪出来了
Hurry up! That monster is back
前辈，你怎么变成这样呢？
Elder, what happened?
进去看看！
Go inside and search
好！
Yes!
里边出现了一只好大好大
Inside there's a huge creature
但不知道是什么东西呀
I don't know what it is
镇定，大家用定心咒
Be calm! Use the "freeze" incantation Together: Freeze!
定！
Freeze!
真灵验呀！前辈，真灵验呀！
It really works!
是呀，是很灵验
It sure does!
真的定得一动也不动！
We froze it in its tracks
大家跳上去！
Everybody, jump up there!
机关？
The archery machine!
小心呀，前辈！
Be careful, Elder!
月池，你去救前辈，我去引开巨尸
Moon, go and rescue Elder I'll lure away that monster
是！
OK
放网！
Put out the net
是！
Yes!
你的手…
Your hand...
我们撒离这里
Let's retreat from here
去看看前面发生什么事
See what's going on up ahead
是！
Yes!
是官兵呀！
Soldiers!
左千户，有埋伏呀！
Hu, they're set up an ambush
青风，月池？
Windy, Moon?!
是爹呀！
It's father!
看清楚形势，引他们进庄
Lure the soldiers into villa
没错，用机关对付他
Use the archery machine to mow them down!
是！
Yes!
想走？
Trying to get away?
不好了，机关被巨尸破坏
The monster destroyed the archery machine!
我们前后受敌
We're surrounded by our foes!
别光站着，先放我出来
Let me out!
对了…快放前辈出来
Right! Let Elder go!
前辈，现在怎办呢？
Elder, what should we do now?
我们先站到一旁去
We'll stay on the sidelines
等巨尸来对付进来的高手吧！
When the enemy comes in, the monster will deal with them
扮鬼都不像，快把面具脱下
Obviously a fake ghost Unmask it
快出去救爹！是！
Let's rescue father! Yes!
寡不敌众
You're hopelessly outnumbered
好，我来救你
I'll save you!
刀剑好锋利，很危险
Swords are too dangerous!
不如用拳脚好吗？
Let's use our fists
跟你说用拳脚，你看，现在搞成这样
I told you that swords are too dangerous!
爹，爹！
Father
你快走，不要理我
Get out of here Don't worry about me!
那头向这边飞过来！
That giant corpse ran over here
不要管我，快去救爹
Don't worry about me! Rescue father!
原来妖怪在这里
The monster is here!
叭呢叭呢吽，风火雷电霝
Abracadabra! Hocus pocus!
风火雷电霝
青风！青风！
Windy! Windy!
中了妖毒？
Possessed by evil spirits?!
姐姐…
Sister!
青风，青风她怎么了？
What happened to Windy?
她中了妖毒！
She's been possessed by evil spirits
那怎么办？
What should we do?
附近还有很多官兵，进去再说
Still a lot of soldiers around Better get inside
别动！
Don't move!
按着她，按着她！
Press down on her!
姐姐！…
Sister!
快想办法救姐姐
Think of a way to save my sister
很辣手，她妖毒发作
She's possessed by the den
很快就会变成刚才那只妖
She could turn into a giant monster at any moment
你这奸臣，害得我姐姐变成这样
It's your fault, you traitor!
我要杀了你！
I'll kill you!
不要，他外面还有很多兵马
Wait! His troops are still out there
留着他，可以用他来做人质
We must keep him as a hostage
现形啦，她快要变尸妖了
She's turning into a corpse monster!
姐姐…
Sister!
最快的方法，就是立刻杀了她
We must kill her immediately
那她就变不成了
Otherwise she'll turn into a monster
不能杀，不能杀
You can't kill her!
你到底是好人还是坏人？
Are you a good person or evil?
有奸臣不杀，要杀我姐姐？
You won't kill Hu, but you'll kill my sister
杀奸臣！
Kill Hu!
这里死多少人都没用
No matter how many you kill here you still won't save the kingdom
皇上身边小人太多
The emperor is surrounded by sycophants
根本不明白民间疾苦
and has no idea of the suffering of his people
你们还是拿我的人头去感动皇上
Take my head to the emperor Maybe it will move him
好让皇上明白我们是用心良苦
He'll be convinced of
忠心不二
our sincerity and loyalty
不行！爹！你死了就群龙无首了
Father, if you die we'll have no one to lead us
还是拿我的头去代替你吧！
Take my head instead
不行，拿我们的人头去吧！
No! Take our heads
混账，人头是不可以拿来拿去
Bastards! What good is it to cut off your heads?
何人在此发号施令？
Who are you, ordering people about?!
我就是通天博学士诸葛卧龙！
I am the learned and brilliant Elder Chu Kot
通天博学士诸葛卧龙？
The learned and brilliant Elder Chu Kot!
原来是诸葛先生，请指点迷津
Please guide us
我指点就是全部人都不准死！
None of you are permitted to die
何解呀！
Please explain!
何解？
Explain?!
人头落地，皇帝还是执迷不悟
Your severed heads will mean nothing to the emperor
那不是很不值得吗？还要解？
You'll have died in vain Need I explain more?
笨猪！
Stupid pigs!
还有她没解决呀
What about her?
青风！
Windy!
这下不好了，驱魔跟元神出窍
To exorcise her, she needs a dose of "yang" energy
我功力不够
I am not powerful enough
现在要快点想办法
We better do something soon
否则迟了就来不及了
or it will be too late
还有什么办法呢？
What can we do?
用灵符试试，不过我没把握
Try this magic charm It may or may not work
也要试试
Try it
快点拉青风姑娘下来，好！
Hurry up and pull Miss Windy down OK.
逐鬼驱魔令
I order the evil spirits to be exorcised
怎么会变成这样？
How did this happen?
好难看啊！
Really ugly!
我把它妖身迫出来了
I've forced the evil spirit from her
现在快给些阳气她，她才有一线生机
If she gets a quick dose of "yang" energy, there will be a gleam of hope
快点，快点上去呀
Hurry up
那快点给
Hurry!
我是修道的，定力不够，不能近女色
I'm a monk. I must not get too close to women
她的样子虽然难看，你们不用怕
Don't be afraid of her ugliness
怎么给呀？
How do we give her "yang" energy?
当然是用口传气过去
With your mouth, of course
用口？
Mouth?
难道用你的耳朵吗？
What then. Your ears?
那送我上去
Send me to her
叭呢叭呢吽，风火雷电霝
Abracadabra! Hocus pocus!
姐姐！
Sister!
男人不怕…
A real man is afraid of nothing
原来是你…
It's you!
大人
Lord, a golden-robed priest
外面有个金袍法师正向着正气庄走来
is on his way here
金袍法师？
A golden-robed priest?
大人，大人！把兵器放下！
Lord! Put your swords down!
还不够气，继续！
Not enough! More!
放下兵器！
Lower your swords!
放下全部兵器
Put all your swords down!
真是国之将亡，豺狼当道
There are evildoers behind every country's downfall
好，你就拿我的人头去领功吧！
Take my head and collect your reward
刚才我看见各位视死如归
The way that you look death calmly in the face
才知道各位忠君爱国
proves that you are loyal to our country
我们的政见虽然不同
Even though our political views are different
但是，我很愿意助各位一臂之力
I'm still willing to help you
外面的金袍法师
The golden-robed Taoist outside
就是护国法丈“普渡慈航”
is the High Priest
普渡慈航？
The High Priest?
宫内所有的祭礼跟法事
All the rites and rituals in the palace...
皇上都会先询问过他的意见
the emperor consults him for guidance
如果他肯劝谏，那就沉冤得雪啦！
If he speaks on your behalf justice will triumph
爹！
Father!
傅大人
Lord Fu, if you trust me
你若能相信我，让我出去见他
let me go to him
好把事情说明
I'll explain the true situation
爹，他会不会出卖你？
Father, he might betray you!
不会，要杀他早就杀了我
He could have killed me had he wanted to
还没醒过来？
Still not awake?!
够了，你不用再传气过来
Enough! I'm going to puke
前辈…
Elder!
宁采臣！
Ning!
左千户参见护国法丈
I am here to pay my respects to the high priest
卑职查出钦犯傅天仇并非奸臣乱党
Lord Fu is not a traitor
实在是忠义之士，并无叛国之心
He is a loyal subject, a patriot
请法丈主持正义
I hope that you will uphold justice
当今之世，太多人是非不分
There are many who cannot tell between good and evil
不了解朝廷的苦处
They do not know the hardships of the imperial court
本法丈今次出游，就是平息民怨
The purpose of my journey is to pacify the people
好，就等本法丈替朝廷安排一下
I'll intercede at court
这些忠臣义士吧
on behalf of these loyal subjects
善哉，善哉！
Amen! Amen!
谢法丈！
Thank you, High Priest!
知秋大侠，你怎么啦？
How are you, Autumn?
女色果然厉害，我要不是集中精神
Women are very tempting If I didn't exercise self-control...
元神都差点被你弄散了
my energy would have been dissipated
千户戾气太重，有损法丈祥和之气
Hu is treacherous and disrupts the High Priest's harmony
请留步
Please stay here
犯官礼部尚书傅天仇拜见法丈大人
The convict Lord Fu is here to see the High Priest
拜见法丈大人
I pay my respect to the High Priest
善哉！善哉！你们杀气太大
Amen! Amen! You have a murderous air about you
还不快点放下屠刀，立地成佛
Put down your weapons
下官身陷冤狱，但是心怀国事
I've been framed, but I am concerned about our nation
素闻法丈慈悲，望助皇上普救世上
You are so merciful
重振国运
Guide the emperor to save the nation
浮世苍生，原是一场大劫
Life is chaotic
虽知苦海无边，回头是岸
Mistakes can always be corrected
我前生冤孽深重
In my former life I was evil
今世有此报应，冤孽
so I must do good in this life
法丈慈悲，法丈打救
Release my soul from purgatory
法丈慈悲，法丈打救…
索命梵音？
Evil chanting?!
不要上他的当
Don't be tricked!
坐下！
Sit down!
他假慈悲，不要听他的妖音呀
His mercy is false! Don't be tricked by his devilish voice!
神兵火急，急急如律令，定！
Abracadabra! Freeze!
逐鬼驱魔令
I order the evil spirits to be exorcised!
南呒极乐世界，西方如来法驾到此
I am the absolute Buddha
你们这些邪魔妖孽
What kind of evil spirit are you!
在佛祖面前，还不赶快现形？
Even before Buddha you refuse to reveal your true appearance!
邪魔妖孽？我现形就是这样了
The spirit of evil?! I am what I look like!
我就不信你是如来佛祖，呸！
I don't believe you are Buddha!
让我们过去看看，是真是假
Let's go over and see if you're real or false
不要过去！
Don't
叭呢叭呢吽！风火雷电霝！
Abracadabra! Hocus pocus!
前辈！
Elder!
左千户那个狗官出卖了我们
The bastard Hu betrayed us
这里有我顶住，你们快走！
I'll take care of things here Leave quickly!
叭呢叭呢吽，风火雷电霝，运转乾坤
Abracadabra! Hocus pocus! The universe revolves
修道之人，心中有佛
May Buddha be in your heart
明知道他是假的，我都克服不到
I knew he was false, but couldn't conquer him
我输了！
I failed!
有你们在，我的法术都使不出来
I can't perform my magic with you here
我在后面开条地道，你们快点过去
I'll open a tunnel in the earth for you Hurry!
知秋！
Autumn!
快点，快点走！
Hurry up!
我顶不住了！
I can't hold out
走呀！
Hurry!
叭呢叭呢吽，走呀！快点呀！
Abracadabra! Hurry!
知秋！
Autumn!
爹！
Father!
就算走脱了，始终逃不出手掌
They've escaped for now but I'll get them in the end
先把捉到那三个押回去
Guard the three we've captured!
领法旨！
Yes!
法丈，傅大人怎么啦？
What about Lord Fu?
他们已经知错走了
They have admitted their errors They have departed
世人应该知道天高地厚
People should acknowledge the immensity of the universe
我刚才听到有打斗声
I just heard a fight going on
哼！你耳根不净
Your ears aren't clean!
记着，色即是空，空即是色
Vacate your mind to attain
善哉善哉！
perfect peace of mind
好冷呀！
I'm very cold
小倩，小倩！
Hsiao-tsing!
你不要离开我
Don't leave me!
小倩…
Hsiao-tsing!
小倩，你不要去投胎
Don't be reincarnated so soon
现在做人好难呀
It's too hard to be mortal now
你对小倩真是太好了
You're so good to Hsiao-tsing
到了这个时候，还叫着小倩的名字
I never realized how much you missed her!
我真想不到你这么挂念小倩
十里平湖霜满天
Frost fills the sky over Ten Mile Lake
寸寸青丝愁华年
Silken threads anxious of youth
对月形单望相护
Looking at the moon and feeling lonely
只羡鸳鸯不羡仙
Envious of lovers, not of immortality
小倩！
Hsiao-tsing!
小倩，你还坐着做什么？
Hsiao-tsing, what are you doing here?
快躲起来，你是不能让阳光照射的
Hide! You can't let the sun shine on you!
让阳光照射你就会魂飞魄散
If the sun shines on you your soul will be scattered
那你就永远都投不了胎，转不了世啦
You would never be reincarnated!
怎么你还坐着？
Why don't you listen to me?
没听见我的话吗？小倩！
Hsiao-tsing!
怎么是你呀？对不起！
Oh, it's you! I'm sorry
我又搞错了
Once again I've made a mistake
我错当作你是她了
I mistook you for she
原来小倩是真有其人
So there really is someone named Hsiao-tsing!
是不是画里的那个？
Is she the one in the painting?
你是不是很挂念她？
Do you miss her very much?
小倩的骨灰已经长埋黄土
She's already dead and buried
我们永远见不到面了
We'll never meat again
原来这样，你可以暂时当我是小倩
If you want, you can call me Hsiao-tsing for now
暂时？
For now?
我明白你的意思，你早就许配人了
I understand You're betrothed to another
我认识小倩的时候
When I knew Hsiao-tsing
她也是这样说，她许配了人
she was also betrothed to somebody else
我是身不由己
It's beyond my control
身不由己？小倩也是这样说
Hsiao-tsing said exactly the thing
你跟小倩，一个是人，一个是鬼
You are mortal; she's a ghost
但都没什么分别
But you're both exactly the same
我们真的很像吗？
Are we very much alike?
是很像，像才难搞
Too much so
就因为像才给了我一个假希望
You gave me false hope
不过，假希望总比没希望好
Anyway, false hope is better than none
客、官！
Excuse me!
客、官！两位请用茶
Here's your tea
等一下就会送饭菜上来了
Your meal will be served presently
两位请先随便休息一下
Please make yourselves at home
这个人我见过，他是…
I've seen that man before He's...
不能喝茶，有毒，这间是黑店
The tea is poisoned! This inn is run by thieves!
真的？
Really!
水烧了没有？
Is the water boiling?
烧了！
Yes
刀磨利没有？
The blade sharpened?
磨利了
Nice and sharp
磨利就快上呀
Everything's ready
那小子马上下锅
Put the man in the cauldron immediately
女的留着今晚暖被窝，天气冷呀！
Save the woman for tonight to warm our could beds
杀！
Kill!
剁呀…剁呀…
Slice them up good!
剁呀，剁呀！
Right on!
停手，停手，停手呀！
Stop!
我有血有肉你都砍得下手
Watch where
你还是人吗？
you're stabbing!
窗门打开了，一定是从这儿逃走了
They escaped through the window
这里很危险，这样逃不是办法
It's dangerous here This is no way to escape!
你先跳上树去避一避
Better jump into the tree and hide
我还没复完，没力气跟你一起上去
I still haven't recovered No energy to jump
不用理我，逃得一个算一个
Don't worry about me. Run!
不，我不会离开你的
No. I won't leave you
这次我们真的走投无路了
This time there's no escape!
真想不到我们会死在这里
I never thought we'd die here
诸葛前辈，都是我们累了你啦
Elder, it's our fault for getting you involved
我不是什么诸葛卧龙
I'm not Elder Chu Kot
我只不过是读过几本书的穷书生
I'm just a poor scholar
我不管你是谁
No matter who you are...
能够跟自己喜欢的人死在一块
I feel fortunate to die
我觉得很幸福
with the one I love
我们以后再也不会分开了
We'll never be parted again
以后再也不会分开，你搂着我！
We'll never be parted again Hold me!
让我在外面，那些狼要吃的就先吃我
Let me be on the outside so that the wolf eats me first
你真是太好了
You're wonderful
你也是！
So are you
永远都是这样就好了
If we could be like this forever it would be great
兰…若…寺！
Orchid Temple!
兰若寺！
什么兰若寺？
What's the Orchid Temple?
怎么我忘了燕赤霞呢？
How could I have forgotten about Yin?
他是谁？
Who is he?
兰若寺有个长着大胡子的
The bearded man in the Orchid Temple
他法力高强
A wizard in the occult
找到了他，就可以对付普渡慈航了
If we find him, we can deal with the High Priest
慈航法丈不是要回京城吗？
Isn't the High Priest returning to the capital city?
为什么会回慈航大殿来了？
Why go to his palace?
法丈连日讲经，有损真阴
He needs a tranquil place
需要静养一晚
to meditate
佛门圣地，难容俗人，千户留步！
Only holy people may enter this sacred place. Stay where you are
天狗食月
This is the hour of the eclipse
乱我丹鼎元气，我要现形了！
My body is changing against my wish
为什么朝廷的文武百官全在这里呢？
Why are all the officials of the imperial court here?
杨大人、江大人、李大人？
Lord Chiang! Lord Yang! Lord Lee!
卑职本来奉各位大人之命
I was escorting Lord Fu
押解钦犯回京
back to the capital...
但是不能完成任务，请听卑职解释
But couldn't complete my mission Allow me to explain
大人！…
Lord Chiang!
怎么是个虚壳？
A hollow shell?
杨大人，也是个虚壳？
Lord Yang is a hollow shell, too?
这里是什么鬼地方？
What kind of a place is this?
你们是什么妖魔鬼怪？
Are you demons?
你们把这些名臣大将的血肉
What did you do with the flesh
摆在什么地方？
and blood of these officials?
你们跑到哪里去了？快点出来见我！
You demons, come out and face me!
你为什么把朝廷大臣搞成这样？
Why did you do this to the imperial officials?
你有什么居心？
What evil intentions do you harbor?
全部都是虚壳？
Are they all hollow shells?!
妖僧，我不管你是什么
I'm going to destroy
今天我一定要消灭你
all of you evil monks
奇怪，全跑到哪儿去了？
Strange, where have they hidden?
知秋一叶？月池？傅大人？
Autumn? Moon? Lord Fu?
傅大人，傅大人…
Lord Fu!
怎么变成这样？其他人呢？
What happened? Where are the others?
我信错了你，现在累死了这么多人
I was wrong to believe you! You've caused so much harm!
你还有什么阴谋？
What other plots do you have up your sleeve?
我们上当了，普渡慈航原来是只妖怪
We were tricked The High Priest is a demon!
朝廷好多大臣已经变成了行尸走肉
He turned many officials into walking corpses
我们快点赶到京城，禀告皇上
We must report this to the emperor
否则天下就万劫不复了！
Otherwise, the kingdom will be beyond redemption
原来祸根就是他
Oh, he's the one who instigated this calamity!
难怪朝纲大乱
No wonder the court is in upheaval
先去救了其他人再说，来！
We must hurry to rescue the others We can talk later
月池！
Moon!
爹！
Dad!
知秋！
Autumn!
狗官，朝廷有妖怪
There are demons in the court
那我不是要理国事了
so I must get involved in affairs of state
多一个人就多一分力量
Everyone must do his bit
快点走，现在是水深火热
Hurry! There's danger everywhere
过了这次大劫再说
Let's get past this hurdle first
妖僧法力高强
These demonic monks have great magical powers
趁他还没醒过来，我们快点离开这里
Once he's awake we won't be able to escape, so hurry!
知秋，快走，不要再打了
Autumn, get out of here! Don't fight anymore!
这里一片荒凉
This is a scene of desolation
大人，你骑我的马走吧！
Lord, ride my horse
索命梵音！
More chanting!
爹！
Father!
我用元神帮你集中精神
I'll use my powers to help you concentrate
回来呀，左千户，你打不过他的
Come back, Hu. You'll never beat him
放下屠刀，立地成佛
Put down your butchers' knives Bow before Buddha!
左千户，不要白白的牺牲呀！
Hu, don't sacrifice yourself in vain!
我错信了妖孽，杀害忠良
I mistakenly trusted these demons and slaughtered righteous officials
今天我要赎回我的罪行
To atone for my sins
我要跟他拼了
I'll fight him to the death
不要过去呀！
Don't!
我不入地狱，谁入地狱
I'm headed for hell anyway
左千户！
Hu!
大侠，风云变色，狂风挡路
Yin, why does the wind suddenly blow so violently?
现在难辨方向呀
It's hard to tell which direction is which
燕赤霞，怎么办呢？
Yin, what should we do?
一路上妖气冲天
Evil spirits pervade this road
千钧一发，不能停下来
Our lives hang by a slender thread
快点跟我继续赶路吧
We mustn't stop. Follow me!
天地无极，乾坤借法
Oh, boundless heaven and earth Help me!
大家跟我一起念，般若波罗密…
Recite the scriptures with me! Prajna paramita...
金刚法咒？
The Diamond Sutra incantation?
般若波罗密…
Prajna paramita...
无知小辈，敢在我面前放肆？
Ignoramus, behaving so boorishly in front of me!
般若波罗密！
Prajna paramite...
青风、宁采臣，避开！
Ning, Windy. Get out of the way!
天地无极，乾坤借法
Oh, boundless heaven and earth Help me!
南无极乐世界，西天如来在此
Buddha is present!
你真大胆，连如来佛也敢假冒？
If you dare to impersonate Buddha What would you not dare to do?
你这卑鄙妖怪，再继续扮下去
You think you can hoodwink the people forever?
连自己都信以为是真的
你怎么扮都没用
I'm going to let everyone know
我要把你的假面目公诸于世
what you really are!
世人都喜欢偶像崇拜
The masses love to worship their idols
为什么你们要跟世人作对呢？
Why set yourself against the people?
我呸！就因为世人无知
It's their ignorance
才会被你乘虚而入
that has allowed you to succeed
就是要崇拜也不会崇拜你这些妖怪
I'll never let them worship demons like you
你别想骗人了
You'll never deceive the people again!
佛法无边，不依我的明灯指示
If you refuse to follow my shining beacon...
只有死路一条
you will be destroyed!
放屁，龙啸九天，万剑归宗
What crap! Look out!
皓天正气，日月齐光
Justice for all!
剑归无极
Swords are part of the infinite!
她的假身被我毁了
We've only destroyed the false outer body
随时会再来进攻
He can come back and attack us at any time
大家不要离开这个剑圈，念经！
We must use our swords to fight back!
道友，我来自我介绍，我是昆仑派…
Let me introduce myself I'm from the Kunlun sect...
这个时候还什么昆仑派呢
At a time like this, let's not separate into sects
大家要同仇敌盖，对付那只老妖怪
We're all fighting the same enemy Destroy this demon!
念经！
Chant with me!
般若波罗密…
Prajna paramita...
老妖潜到地下去，破了我的剑圈
The old demon has stolen into the earth and broken through our ring of swords
大侠，那我们该怎么办呢？
What should we do?
你看！
Watch!
他是什么妖精呀？
What kind of demon?
跟我来！
Come with me!
大家拉着我，跟我飞上去
Hold on to me as I fly
宁采臣！
Ning!
你拉掉了我的衣袖呀
You pulled my sleeve off
你们又回来做什么？
What are you coming back for?
怎么又不见了？
What happened?
是不是走了？
Gone?
别吵！
Keep quiet!
小心，妖精现形了
Be careful The demon has changed its appearance
好大只呀！
It's huge!
小心呀！
Be careful!
月池，看着你爹，我去帮燕赤霞
Moon, look after your father I'll help Yin
知秋，小心呀！
Autumn, be careful!
原来是只千年蜈蚣
The demon's actually a giant centipede!
百足之虫，想变成龙？我呸！
That worm can never be a dragon
前辈！
Elder!
我出道以来
I've never had to deal with
从没对付过这么大的妖怪
such a giant creature
现在怎办？
What should we do now?
大又怎么样？剌他的天灵盖
Pierce the crown of its head
宁采臣！
Ning!
青风！
Windy!
龙啸九天，驭剑飞行
The flying sword!
般若波罗密！
Prajna paramite!
神剑伏妖
Exorcise the demons!
天地无极，乾坤借法
Oh, boundless heaven and earth Help me!
前辈！
Elder!
知秋！
Autumn!
孤掌难鸣，让我们双剑合壁
Two heads are better than one
叭呢叭呢吽，风火雷电霝
Abracadabra. Hocus pocus
风火雷电霝
Hocus pocus
唉，我躲在兰若寺这么久
I've been in the Orchid Temple for so long...
不知道人世间
I didn't know the world
现在变成魔、妖、神、鬼跟人
was so full of devils and demons
都混淆不清
It's hard to separate the living from the deed
搞得天下大乱
The world is in chaos
幸亏你躲在兰若寺
It's a good thing you hid in the Orchid Temple
否则我不知道该到那儿去找你
Otherwise I might never have found you
既然是同道中人
We share the same ideals...
不若我们大家浪迹天涯，替天行道
We should roam this world together and fight for justice
一起结伴同行好了
We should work together
你在说什么？
What are you saying?
我这个人向来是独来独往
I've always led a solitary existence
上次为了救小倩
Last time, I almost died
跟他一起，差点脱不了身
trying to help you save Hsiao-tsing
这次对付妖怪，跟你合作
This time, I've helped you battle the demons...
差点送了命
and almost lost my life
还是各自修行吧
It's better if we go our own ways
到你有难之时，我再来打救你好了
When you need my help I'll return and save you
小心呀，知秋！
Be careful, Autumn!
妖怪还没死呀
The demon still isn't dead
知秋！
Autumn!
我这下真是有难，你不救我不行了
I really need your help this time or I'm finished
真是好的不来丑的来
We must be jinxed!
我顶着，你快爬出来
I'll take care of things! Quickly, craw!
不行呀！
No good
知秋！
Autumn!
那只蜈蚣飞过来了
That centipede flew over!
燕赤霞跟知秋怎么了？
What about Autumn and Yin?
我们被锁着，要想办法逃出去呀
We're locked in. We must think of a way to escape
你说得对，跟我一起你是太吃亏了
You're right! I've really caused you here
我们肉身被困，要元神出窍才有得救
Our bodies are restrained. We can be saved only if our souls can escape
元神出窍？
Souls?
我怕我功力不够
Will we have enough energy
出了窍回不了肉身呀
to later let the sols back in?
这是唯一的生路
This is the only way!
意守玄关，跟我念法咒
Chant along with me
无名无相，不虚不实
The spirit of Buddha conquers all!
金身不灭，元神出窍
Goodness is indestructible
般若波罗密，叭呢叭咪吽
Prajna paramite. Abracadabra!
叭呢叭咪吽，风火雷电霝
Abracadatra! Hocus pocus!
天地无极，风、火…
Oh, boundless heaven and earth Help me!
知秋！
Autumn!
大胡子！知秋！
Yin!
燕赤霞！
回窍！
Soul, return!
我回不到窍呀！
My soul can't return to my body!
知秋，快点捉住元神
Autumn, catch the soul!
知秋！
Autumn!
他定力不够，回不到窍，我来帮他…
His power isn't strong enough I'll help him
般若波罗密…
Prajna paramite...
我捉不住他
I can't catch it
月池！
Moon!
知秋！
Autumn!
太迟了！
Too late!
知秋！
Autumn!
外面什么声音？这么热闹
What's all the hubbub outside?
什么声音？没有呀！
What hubbub? I don't hear anything!
哪一户人家闺女出阁，这么大的金猪
Who's getting married? Such a large golden pig!
这金猪是皇帝赐给傅天仇的
It's a gift to Lord Fu from the emperor
因为他揭发了奸臣妖孽
Since he exposed the traitors in the imperial court
替朝廷立了大功
he performed a great service for the emperor
所以特别赐只金猪给傅家送女过门
It's a wedding gift for Lord Fu's daughter
月池！
Moon!
月池，月池呀！
宁采臣！
Ning!
是不是青风她…
Is Windy getting...
姐姐已经过门了
Sister is already married
你以后别让她难做了
Don't cause her any trouble
我要上路了
I'm about to start on a journey
你替我祝福他们同偕白首，永结同心
Give her my best wishes for a happy marriage
我会的，你保重呀！
I will. Take care of yourself
再见！
Adieu!
有时候人的希望
It's hard to differentiate
真真假假，实在分不出
between true and false hopes
我现在才明白你为什么要避开人间
Now I understand why you stay away from our mortal world
人是善忘的，好多事会随风而逝
Mortals are forgetful Good deeds fade like the wind
无论做过什么事，很快就会忘记了
No matter what you've done it's soon forgotten
这是好事还是坏事呢？
Is forgetting good or bad?
那我们应不应该再存有寄望呢？
Should we have hopes?
青风！
Windy?!
你说不存寄望的嘛
You said you'd cherish no hope!
姐姐，不要再犹豫啦，快过去吧！
Sister, don't hesitate! Go to him!
青风！
Windy?!
宁采臣！
Ning!
快点走吧，他们快追到了！
Let's go, hurry!
你回去吧！
You go back
再见！
Farewell!
保重！
Take care!
上路！
Let's go!